# Leo Azzollini CURRICULUM VITAE – September 2022

### **Personal Information**

Leo Azzollini University of Oxford leo.azzollini@spi.ox.ac.uk

**Leo Azzollini** is a Postdoctoral Research Officer at the University of Oxford, jointly between the ERC Synergy Project DINA at the Institute for New Economic Thinking (Department of Social Policy) and the Leverhulme Centre for Demographic Science (Department of Sociology). He is also a Non-Stipendiary Research Fellow of Nuffield College. His research interests are at the intersection of Social Stratification, Demography, and Democracy, focusing on the joint impact of macro-social phenomena (*e.g.*, unemployment rate, inequality) and individual socio-demographic characteristics (*e.g.*, unemployment experiences, age, social class) on socio-political attitudes and behaviour, including political participation, socio-political trust, party choice, and attitudes towards democracy. His methodological skills include quantitative and qualitative research methods, with a focus on multilevel models and panel data analysis. His PhD thesis focused on how social stratification and the life course shape political inequalities in Europe. His work appears in international peer-reviewed journals as the *European Sociological Review* and *Social Science Research*.

## **Academic Employment**

Jun 2020 – ongoing University of Oxford - Department of Social Policy and Intervention

Postdoctoral Research Officer

Jointly funded by Leverhulme Centre for Demographic Science and ERC Synergy Project DINA ("*Towards a System of Distributional National Accounts*"), grant n. 856455. PIs: B. Nolan, T. Piketty, E. Saez.

Supervisors: R. Breen, M. Mills, and B. Nolan

Jan 2017 – Sep 2018 **Bocconi University** - DONDENA Research Centre

*Research Assistant*, funded by ERC Project INTERACT Principal Investigator: D. Baldassarri, New York University

#### Education

Sep 2016 – Jan 2021 **Bocconi University** 

Ph.D. in Public Policy and Administration, Cum Laude

Thesis Supervisor: F. C. Billari

Thesis Committee: G. Esping-Andersen, C. De Vries, R. Macmillan Thesis Title: *Social Stratification, Life Course, and Political Inequality* 

External Examiners: L. De Sio, D. Oesch

Oct 2019 – Dec 2019 Nuffield College, University of Oxford

Junior Visiting Scholar at the Sociology Group

Supervisor: G. Evans

Sep 2014 – Nov 2015 London School of Economics and Political Science

M.Sc. in Political Economy of Europe, with Merit

B.Sc. in International Economics, Management, and Finance

## **Scientific Publications**

Leo Azzollini (2022). Scar effects of unemployment on generalised social trust: the joint impact of individual and contextual unemployment across Europe, *Social Science Research*, 2022, 102787, Open Access: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssresearch.2022.102787">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssresearch.2022.102787</a>

Leo Azzollini (2021). The Scar Effects of Unemployment on Electoral Participation: Withdrawal and Mobilization across European Societies, *European Sociological Review*, Volume 37, Issue 6, December 2021, Pages 1007–1026. Open Access: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcab016">https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcab016</a>

[Article Coverage]: [European Social Survey Select Findings], [University of Oxford]

Leo Azzollini (2021). Social Stratification, Life Course, and Political Inequality. *Ph.D. Thesis / Tesi di Dottorato*, published on IRIS Cineca, 2021, <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/11565/4035714">http://hdl.handle.net/11565/4035714</a>

Leo Azzollini and Brian Nolan. Poverty, entry **forthcoming** (2022) in *Encyclopedia of Political Sociology*, editors M. Grasso and M. Giugni. Edward Elgar Publishing.

## **Papers Under Review and Working Papers**

Leo Azzollini, Richard Breen, and Brian Nolan. Demographic Behaviour and Earnings Inequality across OECD Countries. **Review and Resubmit** (2<sup>nd</sup> Round) at *Journal of Economic Inequality*.

Leo Azzollini. Unemployment and Social Participation: the joint role of Individual and Contextual Unemployment in Europe. **Review and Resubmit** (resubmitted) at *Partecipazione e Conflitto/Participation and Conflict*.

Leo Azzollini, Richard Breen, and Brian Nolan. From Gender Equality to Household Earnings Equality: the role of Women's Labour Market Outcomes across OECD Countries. <u>INET Oxford Working Paper No. 2022-13</u>.

Leo Azzollini and Geoffrey Evans. How Party Ideological Convergence accentuates Class differences in Voter Turnout: the Role of Age and Values. *Nuffield Elections Unit*, Working Paper No. 2020-1

Leo Azzollini. Doubly Disadvantaged: Unemployment Scars, Young Age, and Electoral Participation in the UK. *In preparation* 

## **Teaching Experience**

### University of Oxford - Department of Social Policy and Intervention

#### 2022/2023

- Co-Convenor and Lecturer in *Comparative Research Design*, M.Sc. in Comparative Social Policy. Hrs: 18
- Lecturer in Qualitative Research Methods, M.Sc. in Comparative Social Policy. Hrs: 6

#### 2021/2022

- Lecturer in Comparative Research Design, M.Sc. in Comparative Social Policy. Hrs: 12
- Lecturer in *Qualitative Research Methods*, M.Sc. in Comparative Social Policy. Hrs: 6

### Bocconi University - Department of Social and Political Sciences

#### 2019/2020

• Lecturer and T.A. in Sociology, B.Sc. in Economics and Social Sciences. Hrs: 27

#### 2018/2019

- Lecturer and T.A. in *Topics in Comparative Politics*, M.Sc. Politics and Policy Analysis. Hrs: 20
- Lecturer in *Qualitative Research Methods*, Ph.D. in Public Policy. Hrs: 12
- Lab Tutor and T.A. in Applied Statistics, B.Sc. in Economics and Management. Hrs: 30

### 2017/2018

• Lecturer and T.A. in *Public Economics*, B.Sc. in International Politics and Government. Hrs: 20

## Conference Activity, Seminars, and Invited Talks

Sep 2022	<b>Politics and Society Workshop</b> – Uni. of Milan and Duisburg-Essen "Doubly Disadvantaged: Unemployment Scars, Young Age, and Electoral Participation in the UK"
Jul 2022	<b>European Consortium for Sociological Research (ECSR)</b> "Doubly Disadvantaged: Unemployment Scars, Young Age, and Electoral Participation in the UK"
Jul 2022	Inequality and Politics Workshop – Nuffield College, Uni. of Oxford "Inequality, Poverty, and Participation"

Jun 2022	European Population Conference (EPC)  "Mapping Earnings Inequality around the Great Recession: A Relative Means Approach"
Jun 2022	Standing Group on the European Union – ECPR "Contextual Cognitive Mobilisation: how the Unemployment Rate moderates the impact of Age on Trust in the European Parliament"
Apr 2022	RC28 Social Stratification Spring Meeting "Doubly Disadvantaged: Unemployment Scars, Young Age, and Electoral Participation in the UK"
Mar 2022	<b>Politics and Society Workshop – Uni. of Milan and Duisburg-Essen</b> "Doubly Disadvantaged: Unemployment Scars, Young Age, and Electoral Participation in the UK"
Dec 2021	World Inequality Conference "Demographic Behaviour and Earnings Inequality across OECD Countries"
Oct 2021	European Consortium for Sociological Research (ECSR) "The Scar Effects of Unemployment on Electoral Participation: Mobilisation and Withdrawal"
Jun 2021	European Political Science Association Conference (EPSA) "The Scar Effects of Unemployment on Electoral Participation: Mobilisation and Withdrawal"
May 2021	Population Association of America (PAA)
	"Economic Homogamy and Income Inequality across OECD countries: a Country Counterfactuals Approach"
Nov 2020	Institute for New Economic Thinking Researcher Seminar
	"The Scar Effects of Unemployment on Electoral Participation: Mobilisation and Withdrawal"
Oct 2020	Nuffield Social Inequality Research Group Seminar Series
	"Scarring and Turnout"
Jul 2020	European Consortium for Sociological Research (ECSR)
	"On the New Socioeconomics of Trust: Labour Market Precarity and Generalised Trust in a multi-national context"
Jun 2020	European Political Science Association Conference (EPSA)

"How Party Ideological Convergence accentuates Class Differences in Voter Turnout: the Role of Age and Values".

Jun 2020 European Population Conference (EPC)

"The Less, the Merrier? Cohort Size, Welfare State Regimes, and Inequalities in Voter Turnout across Societies".

Jan 2020 Invited Talk at Department of Sociology and Social Research,

**University of Trento** 

"Are Bad Jobs Bad for Democracy? Precarious Work and Political Participation in Europe"

Sep 2019 European Consortium for Sociological Research (ECSR)

"Are Bad Jobs Bad for Democracy? Precarious Work and Political Participation in Europe"

Mar 2019 Spring School - European Consortium for Sociological Research

(ECSR)

"Politics of the Precariat: Generations, Socio-Economic Marginality and Electoral Turnout in Contemporary Society"

Jun 2017 Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management (APPAM)

"Turns out it's about Youth: the interplay between social, income, and

turnout inequalities in Europe"

### **Activities within Research Groups and Institutions**

Oct 2022 - Nov 2022 Nuffield College, University of Oxford

Co-organiser of Nuffield Sociology Seminar Series

Aug 2022 - ongoing ITANES – Italian National Election Studies

Collaborator

Jun 2020 - ongoing **ERC Synergy project DINA** 

Oxford, Paris School of Economics, and Berkeley

Researcher and Scientific Committee Member for World Inequality

Conference

Jun 2020 - ongoing **Employment, Equity, and Growth Group, Institute for New** 

**Economic Thinking, University of Oxford** 

Researcher

Jun 2020 - ongoing Leverhulme Centre for Demographic Science, University of Oxford

Researcher

May 2019 - ongoing **ERC DISCONT, Dondena Centre for Research on Social Dynamics** 

and Public Policies, Bocconi University

Member

Jan 2017 – Sep 2018 ERC INTERACT, Dondena Centre for Research on Social

Dynamics and Public Policies, Bocconi University

Research Assistant and Co-organiser of Workshop "How does Ethnic

Diversity Affect Cooperation?" (June 2017)

### **Doctoral Coursework**

• Advanced Topics in Social Dynamics;

- Advanced Topics in Political Science;
- Population Studies and Demography;
- Sociology;
- Political Science;
- Advanced Topics in Economic and Political Institutions;
- Topics in Public Policy;
- History of Institutions and Inequality;
- Institutions in Comparative Perspective;
- European Policy;
- Policy-Making in the European External Action Service;
- Inter-Governmental Relations;
- Public Administration;
- Organisation Theory;
- Public Economics;
- Microeconomics.

## **Doctoral Training in Quantitative and Qualitative Research Methods**

- Multilevel Models for Social Statistics;
- Advanced Survey Methods;
- Econometrics I, II, III;
- Statistics for Public Policy;
- Oualitative Methods for Policy Evaluation;
- Experimental Methods for Survival Analysis.

## Other Research and Training Activities

Apr 2019 Oxford Spring School in Advanced Research Methods

- Panel Data Analysis;
- Causal Inference;
- R Techniques for Reproducible Research.

Mar 2019 ECSR Spring School in Old and New Methods

- Register Data Analysis;
- Social Network Analysis;
- Field and Online Experiments;
- Geographic Data for Social Science Research;
- Archival Data Analysis.

## **Supervision Activities**

Oct 2020 - ongoing M.Sc. in Comparative Social Policy

Department of Social Policy and Intervention, University of Oxford

Thesis Supervisor

- Gideon Daitz (2020/2021);
- Anakaren Cervantes Ramirez, Tommaso Sacconi (2021/2022);

Thesis Panel Member

- Vittoria Baglieri (2020/2021);
- Divya Vatsa, Sophie Weeden (2021/2022).

#### **Journal Referee**

- British Journal of Sociology;
- Economic and Social Review;
- European Sociological Review;
- Letters in Geospatial and Resource Sciences;
- Social Science Research.

### **Language Skills**

- Italian Native Speaker;
- English Advanced (C2);
- French Intermediate (B1);
- Spanish Intermediate (B1).

#### IT Skills

Statistical software: R (Advanced), SPSS (Advanced), STATA (Advanced);

Geographic Information System: QGIS (Beginner).

Document preparation software: LaTeX (Advanced), MS Office (Advanced).

## **References**

Francesco C. Billari (Ph.D. Dissertation Chair) Department of Social and Political Sciences Bocconi University Via G. Röntgen, 20136, Milan, Italy francesco.billari@unibocconi.it

Geoffrey Evans (Co-author)
Nuffield College
University of Oxford
New Road, Oxford OX1 1NF, United Kingdom
geoffrey.evans@nuffield.ox.ac.uk

Brian Nolan (Current Employer)
Department of Social Policy, Institute for New Economic Thinking, and Nuffield College University of Oxford
Manor Rd Building, Manor Road, Oxford OX1 3UQ, United Kingdom
<a href="mailto:brian.nolan@spi.ox.ac.uk">brian.nolan@spi.ox.ac.uk</a>